Guide to the Nourse Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nourse family papers
1775-1910
1784-1853
MS 1390
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.25
(1 box)
The papers consist of a scrapbook begun by James Nourse in 1850, entitled "Family Memorials." Included are genealogical charts, notes on family history, family correspondence, portraits, certificates, and clippings concerning his ancestors and extended family. The materials primarily document Nourse family history and James Nourse's abolitionist views.
Nourse family
Scope and Contents
A scrapbook, begun by James Nourse in 1853 and entitled "Family Memorials," comprises the Nourse Family Papers. The volume, the gift of Mrs. Joseph L. Ruegg in 1984, had been previously taken apart. Its contents, including genealogical charts, notes on family history, family correspondence, portraits, certificates, and clippings concerning Nourse's ancestors and extended family, are arranged in folders which for the most part follow the order of the scrapbook, since Nourse attempted to keep items by or about individual family members together. The papers date from 1775, but the bulk of the items dates from 1784-1853. The inclusion of materials up to 1910 indicates that the scrapbook was maintained well after James Nourse's death.
The papers primarily document Nourse family history. Correspondence is not continuous; rather, selected letters were included which announce births of children, marriages, new addresses and careers or which detail deathbed scenes. Folders 9 and 11 describe the death in Key West, Florida, of Benjamin Franklin Nourse while serving as a naval surgeon during the Indian wars. Many of the eighteenth century letters discuss expansion of the family's holdings through land purchases in Virginia and Kentucky. Most of the later letters are written to James Nourse or his wife. Of particular note are several letters (folders 5, 8, 11, and 14) concerning James Nourse's abolitionist sentiments and the tension they created in the family.
Related Nourse Family papers are held by the University of Virginia Library, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Biographical / Historical
James Nourse (1805-1854)
James Nourse, son of Michael and Mary Rittenhouse Nourse of Washington, D.C., was born on April 30, 1805. He came from a large and well known family; an uncle Joseph Nourse (1784-1841) served as first registrar of the United States Treasury and a brother, Benjamin Franklin Nourse (1807-1834) was a surgeon, who died serving in the Indian wars in Key West, Florida.
Nourse grew up in Washington, D.C. and graduated from the Theological Seminary of the Presbyterian Church at Princeton in 1827. He was ordained and for many years served a church in Valey, Mifflin County, Pennsylvania, before returning to the Central Academy in Washington, D.C. Initially a supporter of the American Colonization Society, like other members of his family, he eventually broke with the society and became a vocal abolitionist. James Nourse married Sarah Harvey Nourse, and they had eight children who survived their father. Nourse died in 1854 on a visit to southern Iowa.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Families; Middle Atlantic States; Mifflin County (Pa.) -- Religious and ecclesiastical institutions; Abolitionists; Clergy; Nourse, James, 1805-1854; Presbyterian Church in the U.S.A -- Clergy; Nourse family
- Inventory
  - Family Genealogical charts, notes, 1850, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - James Nourse (1732-1784), 1775 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Joseph Nourse (1754-1841), 1784 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - James Nourse (1758-1799), 1784 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - William Nourse (1763-1836), 1808 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eliza (Nourse) Chapline, 1796, 1845 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Robert Nourse (1762-1836), 1784 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Gabriel Nourse (1770-1836), 1784 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - William Riddle, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - D.H. Riddle, 1838-50 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - E. Hughes, 1784 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - B. Bull, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - R. Boyd, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Michael and Mary (Rittenhouse) Nourse, 1835-47 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John Nourse, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Benjamin Franklin Nourse, 1836, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Mary Nourse, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - William Nourse, 1835-48 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Sarah Nourse, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Anna (Nourse) Hassler, 1835, 1837 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Joseph L. Nourse, 1836-49 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charles Nourse, 1844-83 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henry Nourse, 1848 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Sam Harvey, 1840 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Diplomas, certificates of James Nourse, 1827-48 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Amos Nourse, 1870 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - James Nourse to Rev. D. Laurie, 1835 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - James Nourse to Sarah (Harvey) Nourse, 1838 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Clippings, miscellaneous letters, pictures, 1840-1910 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Margaret (Nourse) Patterson, 1853, 1861, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Anna (Nourse) Hassler, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 17)